Register of the Felikss Cielens Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Felikss Cielens papers,
1913-1960
66003
Cielens, Felikss
5 manuscript boxes (2 linear feet)
Hoover Institution on War, Revolution, and Peace Stanford, California 94305-6010
Memoirs, writings, correspondence, memoranda, and printed matter, relating to Latvian foreign relations and political conditions.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Acquired.
Accruals
Increments may have been received since this finding aid was prepared. Please check Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat to find the full extent of the collection.
Biographical Note
1888 Born, Latvia
1905 Participates in revolution against Czarist rule
1906-1909 Studies law in St. Petersburg
1910 Emigrates to Paris
1919 Returns to Latvia, and is elected to the Saeima (parliament) as a member of the Latvian Social Democratic Party
1926-1928 Latvian Minister of Foreign Affairs
1933-1934 Latvian Minister to France, Spain, and Portugal
1934-1940 Lives in exile in Paris
1940 Returns to Latvia
1944 Flees occupied Latvia to Sweden
1961-1964 Laikmetu maiņā, memoirs, published in three volumes
1964 Died, Stockholm
Scope and Content Note
Acquired in 1966, with increments received in 1979 and 1984, the Felikss Cielens papers in the Hoover Institution Archives comprise a small but comprehensive set of materials relating to the career of an important twentieth-century Latvian political figure. Nearly all of Cielens's extant writings, both literary and political, are to be found in the collection, as are documents pertaining to his tenure as Latvian Minister of Foreign Affairs in the 1920s.
Like many Latvians, Cielens was swept up in the turbulent events of the 1905 revolution against Czarist rule in the Russian empire, which then included the Baltic peoples. The failure of the revolution, and the subsequent severe repression by Czarist forces, drove many activists into exile, including Cielens. Although a Social Democrat and an opponent of the Bolsheviks, Cielens came into personal contact with many leading personalities of the Russian revolutionary milieu, including Lenin. His impressions of this time are contained in his memoirs and a lengthy unpublished novel set in the period of the 1917 Russian Revolution and its aftermath; both works are to be found in the SPEECHES AND WRITINGS series.
A strong advocate of Latvian independence, Cielens rose to prominence in the Social Democratic party in the new Latvia of the 1920s, and served as the country's Minister of Foreign Affairs at the end of that decade. The FOREIGN MINISTRY FILE series contains materials relating to Cielens's ministerial activities; there are also press interviews from this time in the INTERVIEWS AND PRESS CONFERENCES series.
During 1933-1934, Cielens served as Latvian Minister to France. There is unfortunately little record of this period in the collection. The emergence of the authoritarian Ulmanis regime in Latvia in the mid-1930s, and the loss of Latvian independence in 1940, effectively ended Cielens's political career within Latvia. Leaving occupied Latvia for Sweden in 1944, Cielens continued to be active both as a writer and as an émigré spokesman. Immediately upon his arrival in Sweden, he wrote a number of reports on the situation in occupied Latvia for the American embassy in Stockholm. These form a separate series in the collection.
Cielens's interests included Latvian literature, and he published a number of studies on the subject, including a short work on Latvian drama that is included among the papers. He wrote prolifically until the end of his life, and the collection assembles the articles he wrote for Latvian émigré publications, principally in Sweden. The majority of the documents in the collection are in Latvian, but there are also materials in French, English, Swedish, and Russian.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the repository's online public access catalog.
Subjects
France.; France--Foreign relations--Latvia.; Latvia.; Latvia--Foreign relations.; Latvia--Foreign relations--France.; Latvia--Politics and government.
Occupations
Diplomats--Latvia.; Statesmen--Latvia.
Container List
- Biographical File, 1963-1966. (Box 1)
  Correspondence and printed matter, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Correspondence, 1966. (Folder 1: 1)
    Fragment of a letter from Cielens's widow, Maija Cielena, and a descriptive note from Witold Sworakowski
  - Printed matter, 1963. (Folder 1: 2)
    Printed copies of two biographical articles published on the occasion of Cielens's seventy-fifth birthday
- Correspondence, 1923-1963. (Box 1)
  Letters and enclosures, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
  - Unidentified, 1923-1929 (Folder 1: 3)
  - Attlee, Clement, 1945 (Folder 1: 4)
  - Auriol, Vincent, 1951 (Folder 1: 5)
  - Berends, K., 1963 (Folder 1: 6)
  - Bevin, Ernest, 1947 (Folder 1: 7)
  - Byrnes, James F., 1946 (Folder 1: 8)
  - Čakste, Janis, 1946 (Folder 1: 9)
  - Grosvalds, O., 1946 (Folder 1: 10)
  - Hansson, Albin, 1944 (Folder 1: 11)
  - International Conference of Social Democratic Parties, 1946 (Folder 1: 12)
  - Kennedy, John F., 1960 (Folder 1: 13)
  - Krēsliņš, M., 1934 (Folder 1: 14)
  - Liepiņš, Robert, 1948 (Folder 1: 15)
  - Palkavnieks, [?], 1934 (Folder 1: 16)
  - Rei, August, 1933 (Folder 1: 17)
  - Rusk, Dean, 1961 (Folder 1: 18)
  - Salnais, Voldemārs, 1944 (Folder 1: 19)
- Speeches and Writings, 1914-1964. (Box 1-3)
  Articles, monographs, and unpublished writings, arranged chronologically by title
  - "Latwijas autonomijas projekta galwenas - tēzes," 1915. (Folder 1: 20)
    Printed copy
  - Vēstures tiesa par muižnīecību, 1924. (Folder 1: 21)
  - "Great Britain, the Baltic States and Russia," 1924 February. (Folder 1: 22)
    Typescript
  - Article on Latvian foreign policy, 1927. (Folder 1: 23)
  - "Vozniknet li novaia mirovaia voina iz-za dal'ne-vostochnykh sobytii?" Segodnia vecherom, 1931 December 3. (Folder 1: 24)
  - "Latvijas valdības tēzes atbruņošanās konferencē," 1932. (Folder 1: 25)
  - "Le trio germano-italo-russe sur les crêtes des Balkans," 1939 (Folder 1: 26)
  - "La tragédie de la Pologne," 1940. (Folder 1: 27)
  - "The Drama of the North," Europe, 1940 April. (Folder 1: 28)
  - "La situation en Lettonie et les devoirs actuels du peuple letton," 1943. (Folder 1: 29)
  - "Statement on the Situation in Latvia and in the Other Baltic States," 1943. (Folder 1: 30)
  - Appeal by Latvian intellectuals, 1944 April. (Folder 1: 31)
  - "Nordens stora drama," Svensk Tidskrift, no. 5, 1944 May. (Folder 1: 32)
  - "Tyskarna i Balticum," Morgon-Tidningen, 1944 July 7. (Folder 1: 33)
  - "The Baltic States: Europe Cannot Be Free if the Baltic Peoples Are Enslaved," New Leader, 1945 April 14. (Folder 1: 34)
    Printed copy of anonymous article to which Cielens contributed
  - "The Baltic Problem," 1945 June 28. (Folder 1: 35)
  - Latvia and the Other Baltic States and Their International Case, 1946. (Folder 1: 36)
  - "Latvijas starptautiskais stāvoklis," Latvju Ziņas, no. 76, 1946. (Folder 1: 37)
  - La Lettonie et les autres états baltes dans la politique internationale, 1946. (Folder 1: 38)
    Printed copy in French and typescript of Latvian original
  - Memorandum on Latvian politics, 1946. (Folder 1: 39)
  - "Kad Dievs svētīs Latviju?" Latvju Ziņas, 1946 November 16. (Folder 1: 40)
  - "Eine konsentrierte gemeinsame Aktion für die Selbständigkeit der baltischen Staaten," 1947 January. (Folder 1: 41)
  - "Baltijas valstu starptautiskais stāvoklis un mūsu uzdevumi," 1947 February 22. (Folder 1: 42)
  - "Maskavas konferences neveiksme," Latvju Ziņas, 1947 May 3. (Folder 1: 43)
  - "Maskavas un Vašingtonas ofensīvas un pretofensīvas," Latvju Ziņas, 1947 June 18. (Folder 1: 44)
  - Nāves pavēnī, 1948. (Folder 1: 45)
  - "Rietumu bloks," Latvju Ziņas, 1948 January 28. (Folder 1: 46)
  - "Par brīvību," Latvju Ziņas, 1948 February 7. (Folder 1: 47)
  - "Jauni vēji Balkānos," Latvju Ziņas, 1948 July 3. (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - "Starptautiskais rakstnieku kongress," Latvju Ziņas, 1948 June 16. (Folder 2: 2)
  - "Starptautiskais rakstnieku kongress," Latvju Ziņas, 1948 June 19. (Folder 2: 3)
  - "Ideoloğiskas pārdomas," Brīvība, no. 1, 1948 August. (Folder 2: 4)
  - "Voldemāru Salno pieminot," Latvju Ziņas, 1948 August 7. (Folder 2: 5)
  - "The Strategic Importance of Northern Europe in World War III," 1949 March 12. (Folder 2: 6)
  - The Latvian Drama, 1950. (Folder 2: 7)
  - "18. Novembra pārdomas," Latvju Ziņas, 1950 November 16. (Folder 2: 8)
  - "The Red Inquisitor General: A Historical Novel," c. 1952 (Folder 2: 9-11)
  - "15. maija morāle," Latvju Ziņas, 1952 March 13. (Folder 2: 12)
  - "Politikas un rakstniecības satuve Francijā," Ceļa Zīmes, 1952 July. (Folder 2: 13)
  - "Padomju imperijas valdīšana Baltijas jūrā," Dzimtenes Balss, 1952 September. (Folder 2: 14)
  - "Revolution I faraonernas rike," Göteborgs Handels-Och Sjöfarts-Tidning, 1952 September 4. (Folder 2: 15)
  - "Nacionālā vienība," Latvju Ziņas, 1952 September 18. (Folder 2: 16)
  - "ASV prezidenta vēlēsanas," Dzimtenes Balss, 1952 October. (Folder 2: 17)
  - "ASV pasaules politika," Latviešu Almanachs, 1953. (Folder 2: 18)
  - "Varas lāsts," Ceļa Zīmes, no. 18, 1954 March. (Folder 2: 19)
  - "Vēstures tradīciju nozīme," Ceļa Zīmes, no. 29, 1956. (Folder 2: 20)
  - "Vēstures tradīciju nozīme," Ceļa Zīmes, no. 30, 1956. (Folder 2: 21)
  - "The International Baltic Problem: The European Importance of the Free Baltic Sea," Labour's Call, 1957 April. (Folder 2: 22)
    Typescript and printed copy
  - "Latvijas valsts idejas pamatojums," 1960. (Folder 2: 23)
  - "Baltijas valstu savienība," 1960 January. (Folder 2: 24)
  - "Mana divkauja ar Trocki pie Volgas 1918. g. augustā," Ceļa Zīmes, no. 39, 1961 (Folder 2: 25)
  - Laikmetu maiņā, 1961-1964 (Box 3)
    - Typescript errata (Folder 3: 1)
    - Printed copies
      - Brochure announcing publication (Folder 3: 2)
      - Volume one (Folder 3: 3)
      - Volume two (Folder 3: 4)
      - Volume three (Folder 3: 5)
- Foreign Ministry File, 1923-1933. (Box 4)
  Correspondence, memoranda, and reports, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Correspondence
    - General. Circular letters to Latvian envoys, 1927 (Folder 4: 1)
    - Unidentified, 1927 (Folder 4: 2)
    - Balodis, A., 1927 (Folder 4: 3)
    - Bilmanis, Roberts, 1927 (Folder 4: 4)
    - Duzmans, K., 1927 (Folder 4: 5)
    - Krasts, E., 1927 (Folder 4: 6)
    - Löfgren, Eliel, 1927 (Folder 4: 7)
    - MacDonald, Ramsay, 1927 (Folder 4: 8)
    - Ozols, K., 1927 (Folder 4: 9)
    - Sēja, P., 1927 (Folder 4: 10)
    - Seskis, J., 1927 (Folder 4: 11)
    - Sventorzecki, M., 1927 (Folder 4: 12)
    - Vanderveld, Émile, 1925 (Folder 4: 13)
    - Vecozols, Julijs, 1927 (Folder 4: 14)
    - Vesmans, Fridrichs, 1927 (Folder 4: 15)
    - Zariņš, K., 1927-1933 (Folder 4: 16)
  - Memoranda written by Cielens
    - "Le traité de commerce avec l'Union des R.S.S.," 1927. (Folder 4: 17)
    - "Latvijas ārējā saimnieciskā politika," 1927 February 11. (Folder 4: 18)
    - "Tirdzniecības līgums ar Grieķiju," 1927 February 26. (Folder 4: 19)
    - "Latvijas un Igaunijas ārlietu ministru aspriede Tallinā 28. februarī un 1. martā," 1927 March 2. (Folder 4: 20)
      Typescript fragment
    - "Negotiations with SSSR [sic] about the Treaty of Non-Agression [sic]," 1927 March 10. (Folder 4: 21)
    - "Die internationale Lage der baltischen Staaten und die Aufgaben der Aussenpolitk Lettlands," 1927 March 28. (Folder 4: 22)
    - "Par saimniecisko līgumu ar Padomju Krieviju," 1927 August 29. (Folder 4: 23)
  - Reports
    - Written by Cielens
      - "Pausales ekonomiskais stāvoklis," 1927. (Folder 4: 24)
      - "Austrumu nodaļas darbibas pārskats pār 1927 g.," 1928. (Folder 4: 25)
    - Written by others
      - Report on Polish military, 1923. (Folder 4: 26)
      - Ozols, K., "10 gadi lielniecisma Krievijā," 1927 November 7. (Folder 4: 27)
- Reports Written By Cielens For the American Embassy in Stockholm, 1944-1945. (Box 4)
  Arranged chronologically by title
  - "Die Tragödie Finnlands," 1944 June 16. (Folder 4: 28)
  - "Das grosse Drama des Nordens," 1944 June 29. (Folder 4: 29)
  - "Die internationale Bedeutung der baltischen Staaten," 1944 July 12. (Folder 4: 30)
  - "Die gegenwärtige militärische und politische Lage in Lettland," 1944 August 15. (Folder 4: 31)
  - "Der Kampf der Sowjetgrossmacht um die Vernichtung des unabhängigen polnischen Staates und dessen internationale Bedeutung," 1944 September 15. (Folder 4: 32)
  - "Der aussenpolitische Drang der russischen Sowjet-Grossmacht," 1944 October 1. (Folder 4: 33)
  - "Der Entscheidungskampf zwischen den Russen und den Deutschen um die Herrschaft in der Ostsee," 1944 October 1. (Folder 4: 34)
  - "Die politische Bedeutung des Kampfes um Balticum," 1944 October 1. (Folder 4: 35)
  - "Der Drang Russlands nach Balkan und Konstantinopel," 1944 October 14. (Folder 4: 36)
  - "Ist die Sowjetisierung Deutschlands unvermeidlich?" 1944 November 1. (Folder 4: 37)
  - "Will Moskau seine Japanpolitik ändern?" 1944 November 15. (Folder 4: 38)
  - "Die innenpolitische Lage in Lettland am Ende des vierten Jahres der fremden Okkupation," 1944 December (Folder 4: 39)
    typescript
  - "Was ist das Russland von heute?" 1944 December. (Folder 4: 40)
  - "Die Schrecken und Grausamkeiten des Krieges in Lettland," 1944 December 1. (Folder 4: 41)
  - "Die Uneinigkeit der alliierten Mächte und der Verstress Russlands in Europa," 1944 December 14. (Folder 4: 42)
  - "Die russische Politik Polnen gegenüber," 1944 December 30. (Folder 4: 43)
  - "Die russische Sowjet-Grossmacht," 1945. (Folder 4: 44)
  - "Nachrichten über Lettland," 1945 January 15. (Folder 4: 45)
  - "Der Panslavismus und die orthodoxale Kirche im Dienste der Sowjetgrossmacht" 1945 March. (Folder 4: 46)
- Interviews and Press Conferences Given By Cielens, 1924-1933. (Box 4)
  Articles and transcripts, arranged chronologically
  - Interviews
    - Jaunākās Ziņas, 1924 July 11. (Folder 4: 47)
    - Segodnia Vecherom, 1926 December 21. (Folder 4: 48)
    - Rigasche Rundschau, 1926 December 21. (Folder 4: 49)
    - Vossische Zeitung, 1927. (Folder 4: 50)
    - Segodnia, 1927 January 15. (Folder 4: 51)
  - Press conferences
    - 1927 February. (Folder 4: 52)
    - 1927 February 7. (Folder 4: 53)
    - 1927 February 11. (Folder 4: 54)
  - Interview, Valdības Vēstnesis, 1927 February 12. (Folder 4: 55)
  - Press conferences
    - 1927 March 10. (Folder 4: 56)
    - 1927 April 23. (Folder 4: 57)
    - 1927 May 23. (Folder 4: 58)
    - 1927 June 4. (Folder 4: 59)
    - 1927 June 9. (Folder 4: 60)
    - 1927 July. (Folder 4: 61)
  - Interviews
    - Leipziger neueste Nachrichten, 1927 July 8. (Folder 4: 62)
    - Lieutuva, 1927 August 4. (Folder 4: 63)
    - Wolff Agency, 1927 August 15. (Folder 4: 64)
    - Baltische Presse, 1927 August 19. (Folder 4: 65)
  - Press conferences
    - 1927 August 19. (Folder 4: 66)
    - 1927 August 26. (Folder 4: 67)
  - Interview, Bogholm Agency, 1927 August 29. (Folder 4: 68)
  - Press conferences
    - 1927 September 2. (Folder 4: 69)
    - 1927 September 12. (Folder 4: 70)
  - Interview, Izvestia, 1927 September 23. (Folder 4: 71)
  - Press conferences
    - 1927 September 27. (Folder 4: 72)
    - 1927 September 29. (Folder 4: 73)
    - 1927 October 12. (Folder 4: 74)
    - 1927 November 5. (Folder 4: 75)
    - 1927 November 16. (Folder 4: 76)
    - 1927 November 17. (Folder 4: 77)
    - 1927 November 26. (Folder 4: 78)
    - 1927 December 6. (Folder 4: 79)
    - 1927 December 23. (Folder 4: 80)
  - Interviews
    - Dnia, 1933 March 19. (Folder 4: 81)
    - Jaunakas Ziņas, 1933 March 27. (Folder 4: 82)
- Miscellany, 1918-1946. (Box 5)
  Printed fragment and typescripts, arranged chronologically
  - "Latviesu Pagaidu Nacionālās Padomes Darbības Pārskats no 10. Oktobera lidz 5. Decembrim 1918 gadā," 1918 December. (Folder 5: 1)
  - List of Latvian prime ministers, c. 1940. (Folder 5: 2)
  - "The Atlantic Charter: What It Means to the Baltic Peoples," Baltic Committee for Studies and Cooperation, 1944 May. (Folder 5: 3)
    Printed copy (incomplete)
  - "Apkartraksts: Orrtskommandanta rīkojums," 1944 December 20. (Folder 5: 4)
  - Excerpt from Journal officiel of speech by Edouard Daladier, 1946 July 19. (Folder 5: 5)
- Printed Matter, 1919-1964. (Box 5)
  Monographs and serials issues, arranged by physical form and therein chronologically
  - Monographs
    - Protection of Minorities in Latvia, League of Nations, 1922 (Folder 5: 6)
    - Herbert Schroeder, Russland und die Ostsee, Riga, 1927 (Folder 5: 7)
    - Itogi Latviisko-Sovetskogo torgovogo dogovora, Riga, 1929 (Folder 5: 8)
    - Birger Newman, et al., Balticums Rätt, Uppsala, 1944 (Folder 5: 9)
    - August Rei, Have the Baltic Countries Voluntarily Renounced Their Freedom? New York, 1944 (Folder 5: 10)
    - The International Post-War Settlement, Labour Party, London, 1944 June 29 (Folder 5: 11)
    - Nazi-Soviet Conspiracy and the Baltic States: Diplomatic Documents and Other Evidence, London, 1948 (Folder 5: 12)
    - Arveds Schwabe, The Story of Latvia: A Historical Survey, Stockholm, 1949 (Folder 5: 13)
    - Klāra Kalniņa, Liesmainie Gadi, Stockholm, 1964 (Folder 5: 14)
  - Serial issues
    - Brihwais Latwis, nos. 3 and 4, 1919 April 19-26 (Folder 5: 15)
    - Segodniia, 1929 February 28 (Folder 5: 16)
    - Le Temps, 1939 September 29 (Folder 5: 17)
    - Revue parlementaire, 1948 April 15 (Folder 5: 18)
    - Astoņpadsmitais Novembris, 1944 November 18 (Folder 5: 19)